Guide to the Kenneth E. Schilling papers 1944-2001
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Kenneth E. Schilling papers
1944-2001
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Schilling, Kenneth E.
WCMss.049
3.4 linear feet 5 boxes
This collection contains LP phonograph records and reel-to-reel recordings featuring Whitman College choral groups and the Walla Walla Symphony, lecture notes, subject files, photographs, and concert programs.
Collection is open for research.
Donated to the Whitman College and Northwest Archives by Mrs. Martha Schilling. The accession number is retro-0602.
By series.
Kenneth E. Schilling was born in New Holstein, Wisconsin on October 1st, 1913. In 1935 he graduated from Lawrence University, and earned a master's degree from the University of Minnesota. He then taught at Eastern Oregon College before joining the Whitman faculty in 1944. Schilling married Martha Phillips in 1954.
Schilling's 35 years of teaching service at Whitman College included 25 years as chair of the Music Department. During his tenure at Whitman, Professor Schilling conducted over 2000 public performances with college and church choirs on the West Coast, Canada, and Alaska and adjudicated in 150 choral and vocal competitions and festivals. For 20 years he served as an officer and board member of the Walla Walla Community Concert Association. He was a charter member and past governor of the National Association of Teachers of Singing. He retired from Whitman in 1979. Schilling died in 2001.
The Kenneth E. Schilling Papers include phonograph and reel-to-reel recordings of Whitman College musical performances by the choir and orchestra, and performances with the Walla Walla Symphony.
Also included in the collection are classroom lecture notes, subject files, concert programs and photographs.
Music
- Phonograph recordings, 1945-1964; 1; 1.5 linear feet 3 boxes
  - Graduating Class, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Whitman Choir: Make Awake-Red River, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cantata: Parts One and Two, 3-Dec-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cantata: Parts Three and Four, 3-December 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Whitman Choir: Earth is the Lord's/ Holy Radiant Light, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Greatly Daring (Record 1), 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Greatly Daring (Record 2), 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Holy Radiant Light, Earth is the Lord's, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Music of Life/ Haste Thee/Whitman Hymn, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elks Chorus: Lo, Hear the Gentle Lark, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Riddles: Polly Wolly Doodle Octette, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ye Are Not of the Flesh/Crucifixus: Whitman Choir, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Waldenwoods Concert: Selections, 14-Aug-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Whitman Theatre: Anything Goes, Cole Porter Act One, Side 1 and 2, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Whitman Theatre: Anything Goes, Cole Porter Act Two, Side 1 and 2, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Whitman Theatre: Anything Goes, Cole Porter Act Two, Side 3, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Whitman Theatre: Anything Goes, Cole Porter Act Three, Side 1 and 2, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Messiah: Sides One and Two, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Messiah: Sides Three and Four, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Messiah: Sides Five and Six, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Betty Jane McCarter in Senior Recital: Whitman Conservatory of Music, 17-March-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Julius Baker and Juliette Arnold: Fantasy, George Hue. Ascanio: Air de Ballet, Saint-Saens, 6-Oct-1953 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Whitman College Choir: Psalm 150, Woe Unto Them, Autumn, First of the Four Love Songs, Brahms, May 1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Whitman Choir: Echo Song, Syrinx; The Student Prince, Brother Will, Brother John, Whitman Hymn, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Whitman College Choir: The Student Prince, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Mass in G-Schubert: Whitman Choir and Orchestra, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Messiah: Excerpts-Handel: Whitman Choir and Orchestra; Side Two and Three, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Messiah: Excerpts-Handel: Whitman Choir and Orchestra; Te Deum-Verdi (Side Two), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Whitman Christmas Program (Record 1), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Whitman Christmas Program (Record 2), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Selections from the Creation-Haydn: Walla Walla Symphony, Whitman Choir, and Choraleers, 2-Dec-1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - King David-Honneger: Walla Walla Symphony-Whitman Choir, 8-Dec-1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - King David-Honneger: Walla Walla Symphony-Whitman Choir (Sides Three and Four), 8-Dec-1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Walla Walla Symphony and Choral Union: The Seasons-Haydn, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Walla Walla Symphony and Choral Union: The Seasons-Haydn (Sides 3 and 4), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Walla Walla Symphony and Choral Union: The Seasons-Haydn (Sides 5 and 6), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Whitman Orchestra: John Ringgold, Piano, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fantasia on Christmas Carols-Vaughn Williams; Christmas Oratorio-Excerpts, Saint-Saens, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Messiah: Whitman A Cappella Choir and Community Musicians: Sides One and Two, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Messiah: Whitman A Cappella Choir and Community Musicians: Sides Three and Four, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Messiah: Whitman A Cappella Choir and Community Musicians: Sides Five and Six, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Whitman Choir: O Sing Your Song, George Jenkins Studios, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Christmas Oratorio, Saint-Saens: Whitman College Choir, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Whitman Choir: O Holy Night, Ave Maria, The Lord Bless You, Fantasia on Christmas Carols, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Anthems out of the Silence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dr. K.N. Westerman's Vocal Exercises, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Soundcraft, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Girls Glee: Music with Soft Voices, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Echo Young All The Things, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Collection of Eleven Sounds, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Timothy Russell Notes: Crucifixus, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Various Illegible or misfit recordings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12-33)
- Reel-to-reel recordings and audio cassettes, 1966-1979; 2
  - Shell- Vestal-Rossing, 1966 (Object 1, Box 4)
  - Carol Perkins: Sophomore Voice Recital, 1966 (Object 4, Box 4)
  - Christmas Choral Concert (cassette), 1968 (Object 16, Box 4)
  - Whitman College Choral Concert, 1968-1972 (Object 8, Box 4)
  - WW Symphony Orchestra and Whitman College Choir and Choral Union (2 Reels), 1973 (Object 5, Box 4)
  - WW Symphony Orchestra (cassette), 1973 (Object 15, Box 4)
  - Whitman College Choir (cassette), 1974 (Object 14, Box 4)
  - Whitman College Choir (2 Reels), 1974-1979 (Object 6, Box 4)
  - Jack Medeiros in recital, 13-May-1975 (Object 13, Box 4)
  - Symphony, 22-Feb-1976 (Object 12, Box 4)
  - College Choir (cassette), 1979 (Object 17, Box 4)
  - K.E. Shilling- Children, Undated (Object 3, Box 4)
  - Whitman Music Department, undated (Object 7, Box 4)
  - Whitman College Department of Music Presents Music at Christmas, Undated (Object 9, Box 4)
  - Messner- Mass in B Copy 2, Undated (Object 10, Box 4)
  - Messner- Mass in B Copy 3, Undated (Object 11, Box 4)
  - Messner- Mass in B, Copy 2 and 3 (cassette), Undated (Object 18, Box 4)
- Classroom Materials: Lecture Notes, Tests, 1945-1992; 3
  - Britten, 1945-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Choral Singing in America, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Copland, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Commedia Dell Arte, 1965-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dello Joio, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Diva Decline, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Donizetti, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dvorak, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Fugue, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Eating with opera, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Oscar Hammerstein, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Loose Papers: Essay, Magazine Pages, Program, 1964-1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Henze, Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Hindemith, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Should Business Support the Arts?, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Loose Papers: Student Essays and Magazine Pages, 1966-1971 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Outlaw as Hero, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Opera in English, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Opera for the Birds, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Opera: In Culture Today- Its Place- Winning Friends for Opera Etc, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Up Opera's Ladder, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Overture, Undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Paganini, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Jan Popper, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Ponchielli, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Poulenc, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Prokofiev, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Puccini, 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Loose Paper: Rameau as Master of Lyric Tragedy, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Records, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Loose Paper: The Rake's Progress: Student Essay, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - "Rock" and its Elements, Undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Loose Papers: Rossini and Student Essay, 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Janacek, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Libretto, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Malipiero, Undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Mascagni, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Manon Lescaut, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Loose Papers: Student Essay and Magazine Pages, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Melody, Aria, Recitative, Undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Loose Papers: Wagner Program and Magazine Pages, Undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Menotti, 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Metropolitan Chorus, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Metropolitan Opera House, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Saint Saens, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Salzburg Marionettes, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Loose Papers: Salzburg Festival, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Schutz, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Scrap of paper, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Shakespeare music, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - "Struggles I Have Known", 1965 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Loose Book: Arnold Schoenberg: A Perspective, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Strauss, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Verdi, 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Tschaikovsky, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Loose Paper: Student Essay, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Vienna, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Wagner, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - American Opera, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Libretti- Orfeo, Gluck, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Final Exam Key: Opera (empty folder), Undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Loose Paper: Walla Walla Symphony: Holiday Special, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Bach (empty folder), Undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Offenbach, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Ballet and Opera: Sisters, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Barber, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Loose Papers: Student Essay, Magazine Pages, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Bel Canto, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Loose Paper: Student Essay, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Berg (empty folder), Undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Loose Paper: Magazine Pages, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Bizet, Undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - The Kings of Jester, Undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Meyerbeer, Undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Symphony Lecture #2: Opera for People who Hate Opera, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Mozart, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Survey of Opera 1600-1900, Undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Elder Hostel, Undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Students Opera Exam Answers, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Opera Term Papers, Undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Unnamed Folder: Chronological Order, Undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Opera Recordings List for Identification, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Opera for Final Exam, Undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Loose Papers: Student Essay and Final Exam, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Grout: Chapter II (Lyric Theatre of Greeks), Undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Loose Papers: News clippings, magazine pages, notes, 1970-1991 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Why Opera?, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - The Chorus, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - The Opera Orchestra (empty folder), Undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Grout: Chapter I (Intro), Undated (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Grout: Chapter III (The Medieval Dramatic Music), Undated (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Grout: Chapter IV (Immediate forerunners of Opera), Undated (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Grout: Chapter V (The Beginnings), Undated (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Grout: Chapter VI (Monteverdi's Orfeo), Undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Grout: Chapter VII (Other Italian Court Operas), Undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Grout: Chapter VIII (Italian Opera in Later 17th century), Undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Grout: Chapter IX (Italian Opera in Germany), Undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Grout: Chapter X (Early German Opera), Undated (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Grout: Chapter XI (Lully and French Opera), Undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Grout: Chapter XII (English Opera), Undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Grout: Chapter XIII (Masters of Early 18th Century), Undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Grout: Chapter XIV (Opera Seria), Undated (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Grout: Chapter XV (Gluck), Undated (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Grout: Chapter XVI (18th Century Comic Opera), Undated (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Grout: Chapter XVII (Mozart), Undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Grout: Chapter XVIII (Turn of Century), Undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Grout: Chapter XIX (Grand Opera), Undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Grout: Chapter XX (Opera Comique), Undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Grout: Chapter XXI (Verdi, Rossini, Donizetti, Bellini), Undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Grout: Chapter XXII (Romantic Opera in Germany), Undated (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Grout: Chapter XXIII (Wagner), Undated (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Grout: Chapter XXIV (Later 19th Century), Undated (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Grout: Chapter XXV (Nationalism and Opera, Undated (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Grout: Chapter XXVI (Old Bottles and New Wine), Undated (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Grout: Chapter XXVII (Tradition and Renewal), Undated (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Exam- Moten, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Exam- Moten- Ellington, Undated (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Final Exam, Undated (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Jazz- #1, Undated (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Jazz- #2, Undated (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Jazz- #3, Undated (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Jazz- #4, Undated (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Jazz- #5, Undated (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Jazz- #6, Undated (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Jazz- #7 (Armstrong), Undated (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Jazz- #8 (Beiderbecke), Undated (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - Jazz- #9 (Henderson and Stravinsky), Undated (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Jazz- #10 (Moten, Lewis, Waller), Undated (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - Jazz- #11 (Kruder, Eldridge, Hampton), Undated (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - Jazz- #12 (Lewis and Goodman), Undated (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - Jazz- #13 (Hawkins, Young, Holioai, Tatum, Fitzgerald), Undated (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - Jazz- #14 (Lucenford), Undated (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - Jazz- #15 (Hooges, Williams), Undated (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - Jazz- #15 (Bebop: Gillespie, Parker, Christian), Undated (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - Garner, Powell, Vaughan, Undated (Box 5, Folder 135)
  - Review of Brochure Musicians to "Pool", Undated (Box 5, Folder 136)
  - Tristano, Davis, Dameron, Dexter, Undated (Box 5, Folder 137)
  - Coltrane, Undated (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Rollins Monk, Undated (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - Modern Jazz Quartet: John Lewis, Mingus, Undated (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Taylor, Coleman, Undated (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - Opening Lectures, 1962-1969 (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - Castrati, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Opening Lecture: The Singers, 1969-1992 (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - Records, Undated (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - All About Your Throat, Undated (Box 5, Folder 146)
- Newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, biographical information, correspondence, 1944-1987; 4
  - Faculty Biographical Information, 1944-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Seattle Sunday Times article: "Clock Tower Watches Over Whitman Campus", 7-Oct-1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letter from Aurel M. Kelly, Attorney, 16-March-1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letter from Chester C. Maxey, Whitman College President, 27-Feb-1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Whitman music programs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photograph: Schilling gives private lesston to Harry Wiessner, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fall Concert program, 10-Nov-77 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Unlabled: Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Whitman College Song Book, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Various sheet music: Fraternity and Sorority songs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Various newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sheet music: "The Window Pane", Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sheet music: "A Simple Song from Mass", Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters of Appreciation, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of musical groups, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Various sheet music, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Unlabled: Handwritten notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Unlabled: Correspondence, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Unlabled: Music Building Construction, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Unlabled: Proposed Music Hall Gifts, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Unlabled: Proposed Music Hall Gifts, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Nancy Schilling notebook, Undated (Box 5, Folder 147)